<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="refentry-refdb-bug">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>pullcves</refentrytitle>

    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>

    <refmiscinfo class="source">June 27, 2020</refmiscinfo>

    <refmiscinfo class="manual">pullcves Manual</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv id="refdb-bug-name">
    <refname>pullcves</refname>

    <refpurpose>Update the local cvechecker CVE database and version matching
    rules</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->

  <refsynopsisdiv id="refdb-bug-synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>pullcves pull</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>

    <para>or</para>

    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>pullcves cleancache</command>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1 id="refdb-bug-description">
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>The pullcves script will download the CVE entries from the Internet
    and store them in the local cvechecker databases. It will also download
    the latest version matching rules from the Internet and load them up in
    the cvechecker database. It uses the <command>wget</command> tool for the
    downloads and <command>jq</command> for the JSON conversions.</para>

    <para>If <command>cleancache</command> is used, it will clean its internal
    cache. This will effectively remove the downloaded JSON (and generated CSV)
    files, causing the next <command>pull</command> to redownload and reimport
    everything.</para>

    <para>The pullcves script uses the configuration file of cvechecker for
    the paths of the various locations using the same logic (if
    CVECHECKER_CONFFILE is set as environment variable, then it has to point
    to a valid configuration file; if the environment variable is not set, it
    ties ~/.cvechecker.rc, /usr/local/etc/cvechecker.conf and
    /etc/cvechecker.conf in that order).</para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <subtitle>Command Usage</subtitle>

    <para>The command is simply <command>pullcves pull</command> or
    <command>pullcves cleancache</command>.</para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Return Codes</title>

      <para>The returncode of pullcves depends on the actions it
      performed.</para>

      <para>In case of <command>pull</command>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A returncode of 0 means that the CVE database and version
          matching rules were already up to date</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A returncode of 1 means that the CVE database is
          updated</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A returncode of 2 means that the version matching rules are
          updated</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A returncode of 3 means that both the CVE database and version
          matching rules are updated</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="refdb-bug-author">
    <title>Author</title>

    <para>pullcves is part of the cvechecker tool. pullcves was written by
    Sven Vermeulen &lt;sven.vermeulen@siphos.be&gt;.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
